Guide to the John Charles Denham Album of Watercolors and Drawings
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Album of watercolors and drawings.
1777-1935
1790-1835
GEN MSS 831
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection primarily consists of an album filled with drawings, prints, ephemera, and manuscript poems, letters, dedicatory inscriptions, and notes collected or created by John Charles Denham. The album contains 107 small drawings and sketches in graphite, ink, and watercolor by prominent British artists from the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries such as Richard Parkes Bonington, John Flaxman, Sir Thomas Lawrence, Paul Sandby, J. M. W. Turner, and Benjamin West, as well as Denham's cohort in the Society of Young Painters: François Louis Thomas Francia, Thomas Girtin, Sir Robert Ker Porter, and Augustus Wall Callcott. Many of the drawings are signed but most are undated, and appear to have been added to the book between the early 1830s and the mid-1850s. Several bear small paper tags with references to unidentified "Old 'Water Colour' Society" volumes and folios. Among the drawings are portrait sketches of James Boswell, Maria Cosway, William Cowper, John Charles Denham, and Sarah Siddons, as well as the title character of Henry Mackenzie's novel Julia de Roubigné. The artist most prominently represented in the album is Sir Thomas Lawrence, with fifteen drawings, one etching, two letters, and a signature clipped from an unidentified document; the most prominent family represented is the painter/author Sir Robert Ker Porter and his sisters, the novelists Jane and Anna Maria Porter. Also present are watercolor landscapes by the wife and daughter of portrait painter Thomas Phillips and three members of the Batty family, and several drawings by Denham's young stepson Henry Thomas Hamilton (d.1813). Two drawings in the album have historically been attributed to Thomas Gainsborough and one to John Hamilton Mortimer.
Denham, John Charles, -1867
Bartolozzi, Francesco, 1727-1815
Batty, Robert, 1763?-1849
Batty, Robert, 1788 or 1789-1848
Beaumont, George Howland, Sir, 1753-1827
Beetham, Frederick
Bonington, Richard Parkes, 1801-1828
Callcott, Augustus Wall, 1779-1844
Callcott, Maria, Lady, 1785-1842
Campbell, Thomas, 1777-1844
Cattermole, George, 1800-1868
Cipriani, Giovanni Battista, 1727-1785
Clennell, Luke, 1781-1840
Collins, William, 1788-1847
Constable, John, 1776-1837
Cosway, Richard, 1740-1821
Cunningham, J. W. (John William), 1780-1861
Delamotte, William, 1775-1863
Dyce, William, 1806-1864
Flaxman, John, 1755-1826
Francia, François Louis Thomas, 1772-1839
Gainsborough, Thomas, 1727-1788
Girtin, Thomas, 1775-1802
Hamilton, Henry Thomas, approximately 1794-1813
Hamilton, William, 1751-1801
Harlow, George Henry, 1787-1819
Hearne, Thomas, 1744-1817
Hook, Theodore Edward, 1788-1841
Lawrence, Thomas, Sir, 1769-1830
Loutherbourg, Philippe-Jacques de, 1740-1812
Mathews, Charles, 1776-1835
Mortimer, John Hamilton, 1740-1779
Müller, William James, 1812-1845
Owen, William, 1769-1825
Pardoe, Miss (Julia), 1804?-1862
Phillips, Thomas, 1770-1845
Poole, John, 1786?-1872
Porter, Anna Maria, 1778-1832
Porter, Jane, 1776-1850
Porter, Robert Ker, Sir, 1777-1842
Prout, Samuel, 1783-1852
Pyne, W. H. (William Henry), 1769-1843
Sandby, Paul, 1731-1809
Smirke, Robert, 1752-1845
Sotheby, William, 1757-1833
Stanfield, Clarkson, 1793-1867
Stothard, Thomas, 1755-1834
Thurston, John, 1774-1822
Tresham, Henry, 1749?-1814
Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851
Uwins, Thomas, 1782-1857
Varley, John, 1778-1842
West, Benjamin, 1738-1820
Westall, Richard, 1765-1836
Westmacott, Richard, 1799-1872
Wheatley, Francis, 1747-1801
Wilkie, David, Sir, 1785-1841
Wilson, Richard, 1713-1782
Wright, John Massey, 1777-1866
General note
The leather-bound album measures 10.5 by 8.25 inches, and is enclosed in a bespoke morocco case.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edwin J. Beinecke, 1953.
Custodial History
Album compiled by John Charles Denham; to Frances Copeman circa 1861; to Louisa Copeman, circa 1888; to Frank Tetley, Leeds; to James Miles Book Shop, Leeds, by 1924; to Sir Harold Mackintosh, Harrogate, by 1935; to Edwin J. Beinecke by 1953.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
John Charles Denham (d. 1867)
John Charles Denham was a British civil servant and afterward the secretary and treasurer of the Globe Insurance Company of London. Born in London and the son of a painter of miniatures, Denham was an amateur artist and one of the nine original members of the Society of Young Painters, founded in 1799 and also known as the Brothers, for whom he served as treasurer. Denham was a close friend of the history painter William Hamilton (1751-1801), whose widow Mary (d. 1837) became Denham's first wife; his second wife was Cecilia Sarah Bell (d. 1849), and his third, Catherine Case Copeman (1811-1861), a native of Sprowston, Norfolk. Denham died at his home in the Maida Vale section of London on December 15, 1867, at age 90. He is buried in Kensal Green Cemetery, London, with his wife Catherine and his brother, Vice Admiral Sir Henry Mangles Denham (1800-1887).
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily consists of an album filled with drawings, prints, ephemera, and manuscript poems, letters, dedicatory inscriptions, and notes collected or created by John Charles Denham. According to an inscription by Jane Porter (leaf 2), the album was possibly created as a tribute to Denham's first wife Mary Hamilton. The volume is bound in tooled leather, measures 10.5 by 8.25 inches, and is enclosed in a bespoke morocco case.
The album contains 107 small drawings and sketches in graphite, ink, and watercolor by prominent British artists from the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries such as Richard Parkes Bonington, John Flaxman, Sir Thomas Lawrence, Paul Sandby, J. M. W. Turner, and Benjamin West, as well as Denham's cohort in the Society of Young Painters: François Louis Thomas Francia, Thomas Girtin, Sir Robert Ker Porter, and Augustus Wall Callcott. Many of the drawings are signed but most are undated, and appear to have been added to the book between the early 1830s and the mid-1850s. Several bear small paper tags with references to unidentified "Old 'Water Colour' Society" volumes and folios. Among the drawings are portrait sketches of James Boswell, Maria Cosway, William Cowper, John Charles Denham, and Sarah Siddons, as well as the title character Julia de Roubigné of the novel by Henry Mackenzie. The artist most prominently represented in the album is Sir Thomas Lawrence, with fifteen drawings, one etching, two letters, and a signature clipped from an unidentified document; the most prominent family represented is the painter/author Sir Robert Ker Porter and his sisters, the novelists Jane and Anna Maria Porter. Also present are watercolor landscapes by the wife and daughter of portrait painter Thomas Phillips and three members of the Batty family, and several drawings by Denham's young stepson Henry Thomas Hamilton. Two drawings in the album have historically been attributed to Thomas Gainsborough and one to John Hamilton Mortimer (leaves 63, 67, and 77).
Accompanying the album are folders of documentary material holding an undated album inventory (likely made at the turn of the twentieth century), and an essay by Dr. Frederick Beetham, a great-nephew of Catherine Copeman Denham; the latter relates the genealogy of the Denham and Copeman families, and traces the album's provenance to 1935.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Denham Album, 1777-1856. II. Related Documents, 1935.
Artists -- 18th century; Artists -- 19th century; Authors, English -- 19th century; Painters -- 18th century; Painters -- 19th century; Albums (Books) -- England -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- England -- 18th century; Drawings (visual works) -- England -- 19th century; Pen and wash drawings -- England -- 18th century; Pen and wash drawings -- England -- 19th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- England -- 18th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- England -- 19th century; Artists -- England -- 18th century; Artists -- England -- 19th century; Authors -- England -- 19th century; Painters -- England -- 18th century; Bartolozzi, Francesco, 1727-1815; Batty, Robert, 1763?-1849; Batty, Robert, 1788 or 1789-1848; Beaumont, George Howland, Sir, 1753-1827; Beetham, Frederick; Bonington, Richard Parkes, 1801-1828; Boswell, James, 1740-1795 -- Portraits; Callcott, Augustus Wall, 1779-1844; Callcott, Maria, Lady, 1785-1842; Campbell, Thomas, 1777-1844; Cattermole, George, 1800-1868; Cipriani, Giovanni Battista, 1727-1785; Clennell, Luke, 1781-1840; Collins, William, 1788-1847; Constable, John, 1776-1837; Cosway, Maria Hadfield, 1759-1838 -- Portraits; Cosway, Richard, 1740-1821; Cowper, William, 1731-1800 -- Portraits; Cunningham, J. W. (John William), 1780-1861; Denham, John Charles, -1867; Delamotte, William, 1775-1863; Dyce, William, 1806-1864; Flaxman, John, 1755-1826; Francia, François Louis Thomas, 1772-1839; Gainsborough, Thomas, 1727-1788; Girtin, Thomas, 1775-1802; Hamilton, Henry Thomas, approximately 1794-1813; Hamilton, William, 1751-1801; Harlow, George Henry, 1787-1819; Hearne, Thomas, 1744-1817; Hook, Theodore Edward, 1788-1841; Lawrence, Thomas, Sir, 1769-1830; Loutherbourg, Philippe-Jacques de, 1740-1812; Mackintosh, Harold Vincent, 1891-1964; Mathews, Charles, 1776-1835; Mortimer, John Hamilton, 1740-1779; Müller, William James, 1812-1845; Owen, William, 1769-1825; Pardoe, Miss (Julia), 1804?-1862; Phillips, Thomas, 1770-1845; Poole, John, 1786?-1872; Porter, Anna Maria, 1778-1832; Porter, Jane, 1776-1850; Porter, Robert Ker, Sir, 1777-1842; Prout, Samuel, 1783-1852; Pyne, W. H. (William Henry), 1769-1843; Sandby, Paul, 1731-1809; Siddons, Sarah, 1755-1831 -- Portraits; Smirke, Robert, 1752-1845; Sotheby, William, 1757-1833; Stanfield, Clarkson, 1793-1867; Stothard, Thomas, 1755-1834; Tetley, Frank, 1853-1931; Thurston, John, 1774-1822; Tresham, Henry, 1749?-1814; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Uwins, Thomas, 1782-1857; Varley, John, 1778-1842; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820; Westall, Richard, 1765-1836; Westmacott, Richard, 1799-1872; Wheatley, Francis, 1747-1801; Wilkie, David, Sir, 1785-1841; Wilson, Richard, 1713-1782; Wright, John Massey, 1777-1866; Old Water-Colour Society (London, England); Society of Young Painters
- Denham Album, 1777-1856; Series I; 1 bound volume
  Arrangement
  Series I contents is listed by leaf number. The leaves were previously and lightly numbered in pencil in the upper right corner; v following a leaf number indicates the verso of that album leaf. Titles appearing in quotes were taken from the items; items are undated unless indicated.
  - Lawrence, Thomas: graphite drawing of seated woman, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Porter, Jane: inscription, dedication to Mary Denham (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stothard, Thomas: "Judgement of Paris," engraving (Box 1, Folder 2 v)
  - Stothard, Thomas: "Judgement of Paris," wash drawing (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Campbell, Thomas: "Lines to Mrs. Charles Denham," poem, manuscript, 1832 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - D., D.: manuscript transcription of poem from The Velvet Cushion, by John William Cunningham, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arabic manuscript (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Poole, John: inscription and mock translation of the Arabic manuscript, 1833 Aug 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - R., S. V.; inscription regarding the brother of Colonel Denham (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sotheby, William: inscription regarding Jane Porter (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Phillips, Thomas: graphite drawing of trees (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: manuscript letter, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified artist: engraving of a death mask with quote from Shakespeare's Macbeth (Box 1, Folder 8 v)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: autograph (Box 1, Folder 8 v)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: etching of an old woman's profile, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified artist: graphite sketch of four figures (Box 1, Folder 9 v)
  - Hamilton, William: "Susanna," gray and brown wash (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Royal Academicians Club schedule of meetings, January-June 1819, engraving, circa 1819 (Box 1, Folder 10 v)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: "New Shoes," brown ink (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: profile portrait of William Cowper, graphite (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: profile portrait of Mrs. Siddons "in her prime," graphite (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: "Julia de Roubigné," graphite and red chalk (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: "Hippolytus," graphite, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Hamilton the Painter," newspaper clipping (Box 1, Folder 15 v)
  - Hamilton, William: watercolor of a flying spirit, "Engraved for 'The Loves of the [Plants?]'" (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hamilton, William: "Jethro cometh to Moses in his tent, Exodus, Ch. 18," pen and ink with gray wash (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified artist: "Dragley Beck - the birth place of Sir John Barrow," wood engraving on letter sheet (Box 1, Folder 17 v)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: graphite drawing of a face in profile (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: graphite drawing of a woman with a book (Box 1, Folder 18 v)
  - Hamilton, William: "Anthony and Cleopatra," pen and ink with gray and brown wash (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: "Antigonus Dreaming" [Polyneices], graphite, circa 1795 (Box 1, Folder 19 v)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: "The Dream of Antigonus" [Antigone], from A Winter's Tale, graphite, circa 1795 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Harlow, George Henry, graphite drawing of a male head (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Dyce, William: letter to John Charles Denham, 1853 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 21 v)
  - Flaxman, John: "The Destroying Angel," pen and ink and gray wash (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Taylor, John, "On the Allegorical Picture of the Birth of the Thames, by Maria Cosway," poem, letterpress (Box 1, Folder 22 v)
  - Cosway, Richard: "One of 'the Elements' - Water," ink wash (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: graphite drawing of a landscape with cottage (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Flaxman, John: letter to John Charles Denham (Box 1, Folder 24 v)
  - Callcott, Maria: inscription to Mary Denham, describing her drawing of Frascati (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Callcott, Maria: "Frascati, from the Garden of the Villa Aldobrandini," graphite, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bartolozzi, Francesco: graphite and red chalk drawing of two cherubs (Box 1, Folder 26 v)
  - Cipriani, Giovanni Battista: red chalk drawing of a seated female nude, with clipped autograph (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Owen, William: "Tower at Fonthill Abbey," graphite (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Wilkie, David: four small ink sketches, "Kettle Mender" (2) and "Blind Man's Buff" (2) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Wilkie, David: pen and ink sketch for the portrait "The Earl of Kerry" (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Callcott, Augustus Wall: "Emmerick" [Emmerich], graphite (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Smirke, Robert: ink wash drawing of Eli and Samuel (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Porter, Anna Maria: "1831," manuscript poem on her mother's death, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Porter, Jane: inscription, 1832 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 33 v)
  - Porter, Robert Ker: letter to John Charles Denham, 1835 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Porter, Robert Ker: ink wash drawing of a woodcutter, Caracas, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Unidentified artist, aquatint of birds-eye view of a lakeside village, inscribed on verso: "to J. C. Denham Esqre/in token of friendship/from Christian Fuchs [?], Stuttgart, 22 June 1850" (Box 1, Folder 35 v)
  - Owen, William: watercolor drawing of a landscape (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: "Sacking of the Churches," watercolor (Box 1, Folder 36 v)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: ink drawing of a palette with student color instructions for Henry Hamilton, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: letter to Mary Denham regarding paintings by her son Henry Hamilton, circa 1818 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: "The False Prophet Denounc'd," pen and ink wash with body color (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: "Hananiah" [study for "The False Prophet Denounc'd"], graphite and watercolor (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: [study for "The False Prophet Denounc'd"], graphite and watercolor (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: "Don Quixote," watercolor (Box 1, Folder 40 v)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: "Don Quixote," pen and ink wash (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: [study for "The False Prophet Denounc'd"], graphite, ink wash, and body color (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: [study for "The False Prophet Denounc'd"], graphite, ink wash, and body color (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: [study for "The False Prophet Denounc'd"], graphite, ink wash, and body color (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Denham, John Charles: note describing drawing on leaf 45 (Box 1, Folder 44 v)
  - Denham, John Charles: "The Cottage," watercolor (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Pardoe, Julia: "The Lake of Lausanne," manuscript poem, 1840 Nov (Box 1, Folder 45 v)
  - Batty, Miss: "Lausanne," watercolor; inscribed on verso: "Lake of Lausanne/E F M" (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Denham, John Charles: "Carisbrook Castle," watercolor (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - West, Benjamin: "Paul at Melita - for the Picture in Greenwich Hospital Chapel," pen and ink wash (Box 1, Folder 48)
    General note
    A sketch for the altarpiece The Preservation of St Paul after the Shipwreck at Malta (circa 1789), located in the Chapel of St. Peter and St. Paul in Old Royal Naval College Chapel at Greenwich
  - Phillips, Elizabeth Fraser: watercolor drawing of a Scottish loch, 18[?]9 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Phillips, M.: watercolor drawing of a classical ruin, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Bonington, Richard Parkes: "Fontaine du marché aux Poissons a Bâle," graphite with ink wash (Box 1, Folder 50 v)
  - Bonington, Richard Parkes: "Salinelles," graphite (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Beaumont, George Howland: leaf from a sketchbook with graphite drawing of a landscape; inscribed on verso by John Constable (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Constable, John: letter to John Charles Denham, presenting Beaumont's sketchbook leaf, 1832 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Mortimer, John Hamilton: brown ink drawing of a seated nude male (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Thurston, John: watercolor drawing of two figures (Box 1, Folder 53 v)
  - Thurston, John: graphite drawing of a child and portrait of John Milton [?] (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Thurston, John: watercolor and graphite drawing of five figures (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Cosway, Richard: ink and watercolor drawing of an angel sheltering a child (Box 1, Folder 54 v)
  - Westall, Richard: watercolor drawing of Cupid and Psyche (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Owen, William: "Susanna and the Elders," watercolor (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Dyce, William: drypoint etching of a reclining child, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "Theodore E. Hook, Esq.," engraved portrait, cut from Fraser's Magazine for Town and Country 9, no. 52: 434, 1834 Apr (Box 1, Folder 57 v)
  - "Gallery of Literary Characters, No. XLVII: Theodore E. Hook, Esq.," cut from Fraser's Magazine for Town and Country 9, no. 52: 435, 1834 Apr (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Mathews, Charles: manuscript invitation to John Charles Denham, 18[--] Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Neagle, James, after Henry Tresham: "Edward I removing the stone from Scone," cut from title page for Chapter XIII of Hume's History of England, engraving, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 58 v)
  - Tresham, Henry: "Edward I removing the stone from Scone," pen and brown wash, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Dyce, William: watercolor drawing of a bacchanal (Box 1, Folder 59 v)
  - Prout, Samuel: "Rouen," pen and ink wash (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Grignion, Charles, after John Hamilton Mortimer: "John Milton," cut from Milton volume 4 of Bell's edition, The Poets of Great Britain, engraving, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 60 v)
  - Mortimer, John Hamilton: "John Milton," for Bell's edition, The Poets of Great Britain, pen and ink wash, circa 1777 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Tresham, Henry: "Engraved for Bowyer's Hist," brown wash (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Mortimer, John Hamilton [?]: pen and ink wash drawing of a group of figures (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Müller, William James: ink wash drawing of a Turkish Zouave (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Stothard, Thomas: graphite drawing of a seated nude female (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Varley, John: ink wash drawing of a landscape (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Gainsborough, Thomas [?]: graphite drawing of a Suffolk landscape (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Hamilton, William: graphite and ink wash drawing of a farmer and a shed; on verso: ink sketch of a group of figures by Thomas Lawrence (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Cosway, Richard: "'Tis sweetly pretty," graphite portrait of a woman (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Unidentified artist after Thomas Lawrence: "James Boswell," with facsimile complimentary close and signature as caption, lithograph (Box 1, Folder 69 v)
  - Lawrence, Thomas: graphite sketch of James Boswell; on verso: graphite sketch of four figures (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Hamilton, William: pen and ink wash drawing of two children and a dog (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Hamilton, William: pen and ink and graphite drawing of Ulysses slaying the suitors (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Collins, William: graphite drawing of a landscape with field gate (Box 1, Folder 72 v)
  - Westmacott, Richard: graphite and brown wash drawing of two allegorical figures with thyrsi (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Unidentified artist: ink wash drawing of a man; "Lear" inscribed on verso (Box 1, Folder 73 v)
  - Wheatley, Francis: graphite and brown wash drawing of a landscape with shepherds (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Wheatley, Francis: ink and brown wash drawing of a female figure carrying a bundle (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Denham, John Charles: watercolor drawing of a landscape, painted on verso of an engraved invitation to dinner with the Court of Assistants of the Fishmongers Company, September 29, 1856, circa 1856 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Gainsborough, Thomas [?]: watercolor drawing of a landscape with fishermen (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Hamilton, Henry T.: graphite portrait of John Charles Denham, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Royal Academy student ticket, for Henry T. Hamilton; signed on verso by Henry Fuseli and William Owen, 1811 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Francia, François Louis Thomas: "Cumberland," brown ink wash (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Sandby, Paul: watercolor drawing of a landscape with castle (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Turner, J. M. W.: watercolor drawing of shoreline with cliffs made "at Dr. Monro's - Early Sketch" (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Girtin, Thomas: "Bromley, Kent," watercolor (Box 1, Folder 81 v)
  - Cattermole, George: watercolor sketch for Robert Bloomfield's poem "Farmer's Boy" (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Cattermole, George: watercolor drawing of rural scene with three figures, animals, and shed, watercolor (Box 1, Folder 82 v)
  - Denham, John Charles, after Robert Ker Porter: "Madeira," watercolor (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Batty, Col. Robert: "Dove Dale," watercolor (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Delamotte, William: "Near Meiringen, Canton Berne Switzerland," graphite and watercolor, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Stanfield, Clarkson: watercolor drawing of a hospital ship (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Maynard, Lord: graphite and brown wash drawing of a running deer and dog (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Harlow, George Henry: "Wise Men offering," pen and brown ink, and graphite (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Harlow, George Henry: graphite drawing of the tomb of Michelangelo; inscribed on verso: "Florence/Church of Santa Croce", 1818 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Uwins, Thomas: "From 'Love's Album' a poem by Thomas Moore - a previous sketch for a drawing," watercolor (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Wilson, Richard: "Baths of Constantine - Rome," graphite (Box 1, Folder 88)